Guide to the Ludwig Wittgenstein manuscript notebooks, 1914-1951.
Wittgenstein, Ludwig manuscript notebooks
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Ludwig Wittgenstein manuscript notebooks, 1914-1951.
Ludwig, Wittgenstein 1889-1951.
98 volumes.
Manuscripts, Research Materials
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Incomplete set of Wittgenstein's manuscript notes.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Incomplete set of Wittgenstein's manuscript notes, including several pre-Tractatus notebooks, and notes for Philosophische Bemerkungen, Philosophische Grammatik, Grundlagen der Mathematik, Philosophische Untersuchungen (fair copy of part 2), Anmerkungen, "Philosophical Lecture," and other works. Volumes are numbered 1-105b, but several volumes are lacking: v. 1, 6, 28, 43, 59, 72-73, 80-84, 87, 91-92, 95, 97, and 104. A few volume numbers are also used more than once (as in v. 53a and 53b, 56a and 56b, etc.). Bound in red library buckram.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Wittgenstein, Ludwig,1889-1951.; Wittgenstein, Ludwig, 1889-1951.; Wittgenstein, Ludwig, 1889-1951.; Wittgenstein, Ludwig, 1889-1951.; Wittgenstein, Ludwig, 1889-1951.; Wittgenstein, Ludwig, 1889-1951.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
CONTAINER LIST
- Manuscript Photocopies
  - Pre-Tractatus notebook, 1914 (Volume 2)
  - Pre-Tractatus notebook, 1914-1915 (Volume 3)
  - Pre-Tractatus notebook, 1916 (Volume 4)
  - Prototractatus, 1918 (Volume 5)
  - Band I: Philosophische Bemerkungen, 1929 (Volume 7)
  - Band II, undated (Volume 8)
  - Band III: Philosophische Betrachtungen, undated (Volume 9)
  - Band IV, undated (Volume 10)
  - Band V, undated (Volume 11)
  - Band VI: Philosophische Bemerkungen, undated (Volume 12)
  - Band VII, undated (Volume 13)
  - Band VIII: Philosophische Grammatik, undated (Volume 14)
  - Band IX: Philosophische Grammatik, undated (Volume 15)
  - Band X: Philosophische Grammatik, 1932-1933 (Volume 16)
  - Band XI: Philosophische Bemerkungen - Fortsetzung, 1933-1934 (Volume 17)
  - Band XII: Philosophische Bemerkungen XII, 1936, 1945 (Volume 18)
  - Band XIII, 1937, 1938, 1940 (Volume 19)
  - Band XIV, 1937 August-October (Volume 20)
  - Band XV, 1937 September-November (Volume 21)
  - Band XVI, 1937-1938 (Volume 22)
  - Band XVII: Philosophische Bemerkungen, 1938-1939 (Volume 23)
  - Band XVIII: Philosophische Bemerkungen, 1939-1940 (Volume 24)
  - Manuscript notebook: Philosophische Bemerkungen, 1940, 1941 (Volume 25)
  - Manuscript volume, 1941, 1944 (Volume 26)
  - Manuscript volume, 1942-1944 (Volume 27)
  - Manuscript photocopy: Grundlagen der Mathematik, 1942-1943 (Volume 29)
  - Manuscript Photocopy: Grundlagen der Mathematik F, 1943, 1944 (Volume 30)
  - Manuscript volume, 1944 (Volume 31)
  - Manuscript volume, 1944, 1946 (Volume 32)
  - Manuscript volume, 1946 August-September (Volume 33)
  - Manuscript volume, 1946 September-October (Volume 34)
  - Manuscript volume, 1946-1947 (Volume 35)
  - Manuscript volume, 1947 February-June (Volume 36)
  - Manuscript volume, 1947 July-December (Volume 37)
  - Manuscript volume: Band Q, 1947-1948 (Volume 38)
  - Manuscript volume: Band R, 1948-1949 (Volume 39)
  - Manuscript volume: Band S, 1949 (Volume 40)
  - Grosses Format, 1932-1933 (Volume 41)
  - Beginning of Brown Book in German, 1935-1936 (Volume 42)
  - Manuscript fair copy: Philosophische Untersuchungen Part II, 1948 (Volume 44)
  - Large manuscript notebook: C-1, 1933 (Volume 45)
  - Large manuscript notebook: C-2, 1933-1934 (Volume 46)
  - Large manuscript notebook: C-3, 1934 (Volume 47)
  - Large manuscript notebook: C-4, 1934-1935 (Volume 48)
  - Large manuscript notebook: C-5, 1935-1936 (Volume 49)
  - Large manuscript notebook: C-6, 1935-1936 (Volume 50)
  - Large manuscript notebook: C-7, 1936 (Volume 51)
  - Large manuscript notebook: C-8, 1936 (Volume 52)
  - Manuscript notebook, 1931 (Volume 53a)
  - Manuscript notebook, 1931 or 1932 (Volume 53b)
  - Manuscript notebook, 1931 (Volume 54)
  - Manuscript notebook: Anmerkungen, 1931 (Volume 55)
  - Manuscript notebook, 1932-1933 or 1933-1934 (Volume 56a)
  - Manuscript notebook: Continuation of 56a, 1932-1933 or 1933-1934 (Volume 56b)
  - Two manuscript notebooks in 1 volume, 1934, 1937 (Volume 57)
  - Manuscript notebook, 1938 (Volume 58)
  - Two manuscript notebooks in 1 volume, 1938 (Volume 60)
  - Manuscript notebook, 1939 (Volume 61)
  - Two manuscript notebooks in 1 volume, 1939, 1940 (Volume 62)
  - Manuscript notebook, 1941 (Volume 63)
  - Manuscript notebook, 1942 (Volume 64)
  - Manuscript notebook, 1941-1944 (Volume 65)
  - Manuscript notebook, 1944 (Volume 66)
  - Manuscript notebook, undated (Volume 67)
  - Notes on Frazer's Golden Bough: manuscript and typescript, after 1945 (Volume 68)
  - Manuscript notebook: "Philosophical Lecture" (Volume 69)
  - Manuscript notebook no. 4; manuscript notebook, 1949; undated (Volume 70)
  - Manuscript notebook no. 2, 1949 (Volume 71)
  - Short manuscript, early 1950 (Volume 74)
  - Manuscript notebook no. 5, 1950 (Volume 75)
  - Manuscript notebook, 1950 (Volume 76)
  - Manuscript notebook no. 7, 1950 (Volume 76b)
  - Manuscript notebook no. 1, 1950-1951 (Volume 77)
  - Manuscript notebook no. 6; Last notebook, 1951; 1951 April (Volume 78)
  - Seven fragments, undated (Volume 79)
  - Lecture on Ethics; Letter to Ramsey, 1929; 1927 (Volume 85)
  - Typescript, 1929-1930 (Volume 86)
  - Early version, big typescript, 1931-1932 (Volume 88a-88c)
  - Final version, big typescript, 1932-1933 (Volume 89a-89d)
  - Nine short typescripts from period of big typescript, 1931-1932 (Volume 90)
  - Philosophische Untersuchungen, 1937 version, 1937 (Volume 93a)
  - Phil. Untersuchungen, 1937 version, continued; 1938 preface, 1937-1938 (Volume 93b)
  - Revised continuation of Phil. Untersuchungen, 1937 version, undated (Volume 94)
  - Translation by Rhees of Phil. Untersuchungen, Part I, undated (Volume 96)
  - Das Uberraschende in der Mathematik, and corresponding remarks in Bemerkungen I and II, undated (Volume 98)
  - Notes on logic; Diktat fur Schlick; Notes on freedom of the will, 1914; 1932-1933; 1946-1947 (Volume 99)
  - Bemerkungen I, undated (Volume 100)
  - Bemerkungen I, continued, undated (Volume 101)
  - Bemerkungen II, 1945-1946 (Volume 102)
  - Typescript rearrangement of Bande Q and R, 1947-1948 (Volume 103)
  - Zettel I, 1929-1948 (Volume 105a)
  - Zettel II, 1929-1948 (Volume 105b)
- Manuscripts Lacking
  - See volume 99 for more 1914 writings, 1914? (Volume 1)
  - German manuscript of Lecture on Ethics, undated (Volume 6)
  - Perhaps identical with volume 26, undated (Volume 28)
  - Early manuscript of Philosophische Untersuchungen, now lost, undated (Volume 43)
  - See volume 60 (vol. 59 was likely similar), 1938? (Volume 59)
  - Could have been Manuscript notebook no. 3, missing, 1949? (Volume 72)
  - See vol. 70, undated (Volume 73)
  - "Notes on Logic", 1913 September (Volume 80)
  - Engelmann typescript of Tractatus, undated (Volume 81)
  - Vienna typescript of Tractatus, undated (Volume 82)
  - Gmunden typescript of Tractatus, lost, undated (Volume 83)
  - Unpublished Vorwort to Worterbuch, undated (Volume 84)
  - Final version of Moore typescript, lost; exists in photocopies, undated (Volume 87)
  - See vol. 99, undated (Volume 91)
  - See vol. 93b, undated (Volume 92)
  - Typescript of final version of Phil. Untersuchungen, lost, undated (Volume 95)
  - Could be typescript on Godel, not accounted for, undated (Volume 97)
  - See vol. 103, undated (Volume 104)